

Todd M. Ellis

DATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Greater Hobart Region, Tasmania, Australia March 2024

□+61466683552 | ≥ toddellis.wa@gmail.com | ⊙ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | ⊠ q6vTAroAAAAJ | № Todd-Ellis-4 |

otoddellis | tmichaelellis

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY.

I'm a data analyst and early career researcher with a varied background in forest ecology, pyrogeography, climate change, geospatial science, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst and researcher in a variety of laboratory, field, and office settings throughout the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers in institutional policies and procedures, as well as methodological approaches to statistical analysis; and managed both complex and transformative projects for higher education, government agencies, and private industry. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

As at 2024-03-17, I have 3 peer-reviewed publications including 2 first-author publications. I have received a total of 83 or 115 citations based on Scopus and Google Scholar, respectively, with an h-index of 3 in both sources.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania

2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

Master of Science, Geography

Bellingham, WA, USA

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography and Geology

San Marcos, TX, USA

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

2007 - 2012

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Data Insights Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Student Services and Operations (full-time)

2023-01 - present

- Managing the development and implementation of a transformative statewide program to improve equity of access to higher education
- Leading the development of statistical models and reporting tools for managing offers and course quotas
- Streamlining and automating the higher education admissions system for school leavers
- Providing insights and consultations to institutional and external stakeholders

Adjunct Researcher

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - 2023-03

- · Developed complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- · Oversaw multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- Managed custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- Collaborated with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Data Analyst

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - 2023-01

- Developed statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managed design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- Designed and implemented programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- Oversaw development of internal reporting and statistical packages

PUBLICATIONS		
Williamson, G.J., Ellis, T.M. , and Bowman, D.M.J.S. (2022). D	<u> </u>	7 -1441
1 Landsat Imagery to Map Fine-Grained Fire Mosaics in Lowlar Northern Australia. Fire, 5(5), 160. doi:10.3390/fire5050160	nd Eucalyptus Savanna in Kakadu National Park,	7 citations
Ellis, T.M. , Bowman, D.M.J.S., Jain, P., Flannigan, M.D., and V	Williamson, G.J. (2022). Global increase in	
wildfire risk due to climate-driven declines in fuel moisture.		71 citations
doi:10.1111/gcb.16006	3,7, (,,	
Ellis, T.M., and Flower, A. (2017). A multicentury dendrochro	pnological reconstruction of western spruce	
3 budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands, northeaste	rn Washington. Canadian Journal of Forest	5 citations
Research, 47(9), 1266-1277. doi:10.1139/cjfr-2016-0399		
CONSULTING		
RESEARCH		
2020-08 Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite image	ry	AUDĆ1 000
Frontier Development Lab		AUD\$1,000
2019-06 Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity		USD\$2,500
USDA Forest Service		03032,300
2018-08 Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth USDA Forest Service	sensitivity to climate	USD\$2,500
MANUSCRIPT REVIEWER		
Climatic Change, <u>Earth's Future</u> , <u>Fire Ecology</u> , <u>Global Chan</u>	ge Biology, New Phytologist	
HONOURS		
GRANTS, SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS		
2023-09 Student Services and Operations (SSO) Division Student	Focus Award	AUD\$50
University of Tasmania		7,02,700
2022-11 Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Awa	rd	AUD\$50
University of Tasmania		
2021-10 NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Pri Australian Museum	ze for Applied Environmental Research	AUD\$10,000
2020-08 Bushfire Data Quest 2020		
Frontier Development Lab		AUD\$1,000
2019-09 Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)		
NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub		AUD\$28,000 p.a
2019-09 NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3	.5x)	AUDÉE 000
NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub		AUD\$5,000 p.a
OUTREACH		

CONFERENCES AND PRESENTATIONS

2022-12	Removing Barriers and transforming access to tertiary education: The Schools Recommendation Program in Tasmania	Macquarie Park,	
	Australasian Association for Institutional Research Forum 2022	NSW	
2022-06	Dynamic mapping and analysis of fire regimes, past, present, and future	Wollongong, NSW	
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Showcase 2022 (poster)		
2021-05	Fuel moisture trend tool	Wallangang NCW	
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2021 (poster)	Wollongong, NSW	
2020-03	Changes in moisture availability drive fire risk	Wollongong, NSW	
	Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Researchers' Meeting 2020 (presentation)		